<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title></title>
	<atom:link href="https://halcyonschool.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://halcyonschool.com</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 11:24:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.6</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/cropped-Untitled-design-8-32x32.png</url>
	<title></title>
	<link>https://halcyonschool.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Why Families Should Consider an IB School</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/why-families-should-consider-an-ib-school/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Halcyon London International School]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 16:25:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[International Baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ib curriculum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ib school]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=18609</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With just under two million students worldwide, the International Baccalaureate (IB) and IB schools have seen an increased popularity in the UK, with 130 schools now offering the Diploma Programme (IBDP), and an increasing number looking to offer the Middle Years (IBMYP) and Primary Years Programmes (IBPYP). Natalie Stark, Admissions Director at Halcyon London International [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="341" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Why-Consider-and-IB-School_Blog_Banner-1024x341.png" alt="Why Families Should Consider An IB School. Image of Admissions Director, Natalie Stark" class="wp-image-18610" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Why-Consider-and-IB-School_Blog_Banner-1024x341.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Why-Consider-and-IB-School_Blog_Banner-300x100.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Why-Consider-and-IB-School_Blog_Banner-768x256.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Why-Consider-and-IB-School_Blog_Banner-600x200.png 600w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Why-Consider-and-IB-School_Blog_Banner.png 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>With just under two million students worldwide, the International Baccalaureate (IB) and IB schools have seen an increased popularity in the UK, with 130 schools now offering the Diploma Programme (IBDP), and an increasing number looking to offer the Middle Years (IBMYP) and Primary Years Programmes (IBPYP). Natalie Stark, Admissions Director at Halcyon London International School explains the advantages of attending an IB school.</p>



<p>Choosing a secondary school in the UK is often a daunting experience, with the seeming pressure to begin research and preparation almost from birth.&nbsp; In the Central London independent sector alone, there is a vast array of options for families to consider. Increasingly, families are moving away from the British system, with its well known constraints; the extensive <a href="https://nuk-tnl-editorial-prod-staticassets.s3.amazonaws.com/2022/education-commission/Times%20Education%20Commission%20final%20report.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Times Education Commission Report</a> concluded that the system is ‘failing on every measure’.&nbsp; By contrast, the International Baccalaureate Organization has published <a href="https://www.ibo.org/globalassets/new-structure/research/pdfs/key-findings-from-research-on-the-impact-of-the-dp-en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">research</a> suggesting that IB students attain higher levels of critical thinking, global mindedness and academic attainment than their non-IB peers. No wonder IB schools are growing in popularity.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">IB Schools and University Admissions</h2>



<p>The research compares outcomes of UK IB students to A Level students: IB students are ‘three times more likely to enrol at a top 20 higher education institution and 40% more likely to achieve at least an upper second-class honours degree and 7% more likely to earn a first-class honours degree compared to matched A level students’ (Duxbury et al 2021). This can be attributed to the embedding of critical thinking skills across the curriculum and in the Theory of Knowledge course (reflecting on how to question what we claim to know). Additionally, students undertake a 4000 word Extended Essay and a wider range of subjects, including mathematics and a second language, through to the end of secondary school.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Holistic IB Curriculum Inspires Young Minds</h3>



<p>The goals of the IB are not just focused on university entry. It is also a holistic programme aiming to develop &#8216;inquiring, knowledgeable and caring young people who help to create a better and more peaceful world&#8217;. The <a href="https://halcyonschool.com/academics/curriculum/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://halcyonschool.com/academics/curriculum/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IBMYP</a> promotes this through Creativity, Activity, Service projects (CAS), encouraging pupils to think creatively, maintain a healthy lifestyle, and give back to their local communities.&nbsp;There is also a focus in the MYP on interdisciplinary units (IDUs). Thanks to our Marylebone location, London became our classroom. Students recently undertook IDU projects exploring the relationship between animal behaviour, mathematical analysis and ethical habitat design at ZSL London Zoo, and investigating societal perspectives on crime and punishment at the Tower of London.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">IB Curriculum Develops Student Agency</h4>



<p>Activities such as these further embed the learning goals that weave throughout the IB curriculum.&nbsp; <a href="https://halcyonschool.com/blog/inquiry-based-learning/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IB students are encouraged to problem solve and take initiative in their own learning</a> with student agency and voice a core value at Halcyon London International School.&nbsp; An IB school allows students ample space and opportunity to discover their own unique interests and strengths.&nbsp; Students are given constant opportunities to increase their cultural awareness and, consequently, engage more fully in an increasingly globalised world as part of the IB mission.&nbsp; For parents and guardians of students considering the next steps of their educational journey, the IB is a fantastic offering for a wide-ranging, high-achieving and well-rounded education.</p>



<p>As an IB school, we are proud of the academic rigour and personal development that we achieve through our approach to the curriculum. We believe in the transformative power of the education we offer. If you haven&#8217;t yet considered an IB school, we would encourage you to do so. We have several upcoming Open Houses or can arrange a private tour. Follow the link below to find out more.</p>



<p><a href="https://halcyonschool.com/open-house-2024-entry/?utm_source=Families+Choose+IB+School&amp;utm_medium=Blog&amp;utm_campaign=2024+entry&amp;utm_id=OH+Reg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Book an Open House at Halcyon London International School</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Inquiry-Based Learning on Discovery Day</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/inquiry-based-learning-on-discovery-day/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Halcyon London International School]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 13:27:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[International Baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inquiry based learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fbv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fundamental british values]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=19311</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This year, we have re-envisioned our Community Day into a Discovery Day. This exploratory reframe better reflects the inquiry-based nature of these learning experiences, which span across London, from Kew Gardens to London&#8217;s Royal Air Force Museum and Tate Britain, among many other fine local institutions. Discovery Days are an embedded part of the IB [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="229" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Inquiry-Based-Learning-on-Discovery-Day_Oct-24-1-1024x229.png" alt="" class="wp-image-19315" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Inquiry-Based-Learning-on-Discovery-Day_Oct-24-1-1024x229.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Inquiry-Based-Learning-on-Discovery-Day_Oct-24-1-300x67.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Inquiry-Based-Learning-on-Discovery-Day_Oct-24-1-768x172.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Inquiry-Based-Learning-on-Discovery-Day_Oct-24-1.png 1146w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>This year, we have re-envisioned our Community Day into a Discovery Day. This exploratory reframe better reflects the inquiry-based nature of these learning experiences, which span across London, from Kew Gardens to London&#8217;s Royal Air Force Museum and Tate Britain, among many other fine local institutions.</p>



<p>Discovery Days are an embedded part of the IB programme, designed to offer high-quality, real-world learning outside the classroom.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Grade 6</strong></p>



<p>Burgeoning Halcyon scientist Luna reflects on her experience at Kew Gardens: <em>&#8220;We went to Kew Gardens with a brilliant tour guide who taught us how to measure different aspects of ecosystems like soil, temperature, moisture and humidity. We compared the outside conditions with the Palm House, a giant greenhouse containing a tropical rainforest.</em></p>



<p><em>&#8220;Inside, it was really hot and humid, and we learnt about plants with cancer-fighting properties, which was fascinating.</em></p>



<p><em>&#8220;We then explored another glasshouse containing different biomes, including desert, temperate rainforest, tropical ferns and rainforest sections. Having just studied carnivorous plants in science, we were excited to spot pitcher plants in the desert section.</em></p>



<p><em>&#8220;We also saw plants used to cure diseases. As we wandered around taking photographs, we discovered a bridge over a pond with a massive fish and impressively large lily pads. The pathways were lined with hanging vines that kept hitting our faces, and the humidity created water droplets everywhere.</em></p>



<p><em>&#8220;Instead of just looking things up online, we got to experience everything in person. Back at school, we created a Venn diagram comparing the tropical rainforest and urban ecosystem, noting the significant differences in temperature and soil moisture levels between the two environments.&#8221;</em></p>



<p><strong>Grade 7</strong></p>



<p>Halcyon MYP and DP English B Teacher, Rahana Ahmed, says: <em>&#8220;During the visit to the RAF Museum, students engaged in an immersive experience that brought history, technology and human stories to life.</em></p>



<p><em>The museum&#8217;s extensive collection of aircraft, exhibits and interactive displays offered an opportunity for students to explore the history of aviation, the role of the Royal Air Force (RAF) in global conflicts and the technological innovations that have shaped modern flight.</em></p>



<p><em>&#8220;Through interactive simulations and hands-on displays, students had the opportunity to experience what it&#8217;s like to be a pilot or an engineer. They engaged in flight simulations and learnt about the science of flight by participating in a workshop where they prepared an aircraft wing using newspaper and glue to test its design, demonstrating the challenges of aviation.&#8221;</em></p>



<p><strong>Grade 8</strong></p>



<p>Halcyon Learning Systems Coordinator Guillermo Afonso, who was instrumental in organising and facilitating Discovery Day, reflects on the Grade 8 trip: <em>&#8220;Our Grade 8 students embarked on an exciting journey to Canary Wharf, discovering a part of London many had never seen before! Guided by an AI-powered bot, they dived into research, asking brilliant questions about the finance sector&#8217;s role in shaping their city. The highlight? A fascinating tour from Insider London, where students explored the architecture and history of the area. From finance to architecture—and even estimating the volume of One Canada Square—it was an unforgettable adventure of learning and exploration!&#8221;</em></p>



<p><strong>Grade 9</strong></p>



<p>Meanwhile, Halcyon Art Teacher Sue Dance shares a few highlights from the Grade 9 trip to Tate Britain: <em>&#8220;Grade 9 had a wonderful day at Tate Britain discovering two specific art installations/murals created by two Black artists, Alvaro Barrington and Chris Ofili.</em></p>



<p><em>&#8220;Students spent time investigating the materials and images that Alvaro Barrington used in the three sections of his installation called &#8220;Grace&#8221;, referencing his life with the three women who shaped his identity: his grandmother, mother and sister. Students were able to touch areas of the installation and take detailed photographs, allowing them to analyse these specific elements.</em></p>



<p><em>&#8220;The second piece was a very moving mural painting by Chris Ofili set on three walls above the staircase in the Museum called &#8220;Requiem&#8221;, giving students an opportunity to explore his self-expression through a task of &#8220;SEE THINK WONDER&#8221; about the particular tragedy of the Grenfell Tower disaster. Students investigated the way Ofili used symbolism to express emotions of loss and hope, paying homage to artist Khadija Saye, who tragically died in the disaster.</em></p>



<p><em>&#8220;Before we left the gallery, we took a little discovery through other rooms, giving Grade 9 a chance to look at Turner&#8217;s paintings and Pop Art paintings which they have been researching in our art classes!</em></p>



<p><em>&#8220;This was a wonderful opportunity for our students to understand how the British values of liberty (artists expressing their voice through their work) are supported in these public institutions.&#8221;</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Halcyon marks Black History Month</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/halcyon-marks-black-history-month/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Halcyon London International School]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 13:24:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Our Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fbv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fundamental british values]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bhm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[black history month]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=19306</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In alignment with UK Black History Month,, Halcyon has recognised the role of the black community, both globally and locally. Framed under the theme &#8216;Reclaiming Narratives&#8217;, we have recognised the contribution of the black community whilst equally examining where stories haven&#8217;t been acknowledged. The focus, according to Halcyon Geography and Individuals and Societies teacher Shah-Noor [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="229" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-marks-Black-History-Month_Oct-24-1024x229.png" alt="" class="wp-image-19308" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-marks-Black-History-Month_Oct-24-1024x229.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-marks-Black-History-Month_Oct-24-300x67.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-marks-Black-History-Month_Oct-24-768x172.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-marks-Black-History-Month_Oct-24.png 1146w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p>In alignment with UK Black History Month,, Halcyon has recognised the role of the black community, both globally and locally. Framed under the theme &#8216;Reclaiming Narratives&#8217;, we have recognised the contribution of the black community whilst equally examining where stories haven&#8217;t been acknowledged.</p>



<p>The focus, according to Halcyon Geography and Individuals and Societies teacher Shah-Noor Ashraf, who supported the delivery of Black History Month at Halcyon, &#8220;is about correcting and recognising these historical inaccuracies and spotlighting these important stories and events.&#8221;</p>



<p>Shah-Noor Ashraf says, &#8220;I think we have to get into a position where people recognise the black community every day and feel free to speak about it with confidence. We shouldn&#8217;t be constrained to a singular view of the school curriculum. We are here to do much more to further our engagement with the wider community, not just this month but every month.&#8221;</p>



<p>Black History Month has touched every subject – from Chemistry and Geography to languages like German and our Mother Tongue Language Programmes &#8211; with staff working collaboratively to weave Black History Month into their curriculum.</p>



<p>Research projects included students unearthing remarkable people and stories, many of whom have fallen through the cracks of time and visibility.. Examples include trailblazing designer Kitty Black Perkins, who created the first official black Barbie (1979); or in chemistry, Professor Robert Mokaya &#8211; who stands among the less than 1 per cent of black professors &#8211; despite leading groundbreaking discoveries into porous materials, including synthesis and use as adsorbents, catalysts and energy materials.</p>



<p>Similar research projects extended into our languages programme. In German lessons, taught by Andrea Milde, students learned about the lived experiences of Afro-Germans (<em>Afrodeutsche</em>). Ms Milde shares that the students chose video clips (in German language, of course) according to their interests before discussing their findings in German.</p>



<p>Ms Milde says: &#8220;Being an important but often overlooked part of German history and culture, the idea was to raise awareness and connect the topic to themes we have already worked on and/or which are yet to come, rather than treating it as a one-off activity.&#8221;</p>



<p>For example, students learned about the Diek family, who have been living in Germany for over 130 years and yet still experience discrimination. In another class, they listened to Alpha Dia&#8217;s own take on his journey to become a supermodel.</p>



<p>To further materialise Black History Month at Halcyon, History Teacher Hannah Austin, alongside Shah-Noor Ashraf, organised a whole-school assembly. Part of this featured Grade 10 students presenting research on overlooked people who have specifically made contributions to the United Kingdom.</p>



<p>One example was Grade 10 student Luisa, who studied British activist, journalist, feminist and founder of The Notting Hill Carnival, Claudia Jones. Luisa says: &#8220;Before Black History Month, and studying this topic in History, I didn&#8217;t know who Claudia Jones was, but the reality is we should all know who she is.&#8221;</p>



<p>Luisa says learning about Claudia Jones deepened her understanding of not only the rich international history of the Notting Hill Carnival but also its connection with her Brazilian heritage.</p>



<p>&#8220;Everything was new to me, including all the remarkable identities that were shared at the assembly. When I discovered Claudia Jones, I was really interested because of her story; she was born in Trinidad, then she got deported to the US and later arrived in Britain. She continued fighting and didn&#8217;t stop; she kept making an impact.&#8221;</p>



<p>Luisa adds that the project extended beyond her own research into Claudia Jones and magnified the importance of Black History.</p>



<p>&#8220;I think it&#8217;s very important to understand diversity. It&#8217;s important to understand your story to understand who you are. If you don&#8217;t understand the past, the legacy that people leave behind, then you can&#8217;t look forward. We often overlook people and stories when we learn history.</p>



<p>&#8220;There isn&#8217;t only one perspective, there are multiple perspectives, so it makes us rethink everything we have learned in history. That was one of the important parts of Black History Month, to recognise the people who have been overlooked based on the colour of their skin.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Halcyon at the IB World Conference</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/halcyon-at-the-ib-world-conference/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Halcyon London International School]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 13:17:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[International Baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Educational Technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IB world conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innovation team]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[edtech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IB]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=19299</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Faye Ellis Digital Learning Coach, writes up her experience of presenting at the IB World Conference in Budapest. Last week, Farah Ahmed and I attended the IB World Conference 2024 in Budapest (along with our new Director, Jeff Lippman) to represent Halcyon’s Innovation Team and collaborate with educators from IB schools around the world! As [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="229" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-at-IB-World-Conference_Oct-24-1024x229.png" alt="" class="wp-image-19301" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-at-IB-World-Conference_Oct-24-1024x229.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-at-IB-World-Conference_Oct-24-300x67.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-at-IB-World-Conference_Oct-24-768x172.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Blog-Web-Banner_Halcyon-at-IB-World-Conference_Oct-24.png 1146w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-medium-font-size"><em>Faye Ellis Digital Learning Coach, writes up her experience of presenting at the IB World Conference in Budapest.</em></p>



<p>Last week, Farah Ahmed and I attended the IB World Conference 2024 in Budapest (along with our new Director, Jeff Lippman) to represent Halcyon’s Innovation Team and collaborate with educators from IB schools around the world! As part of the conference, I was also invited to lead two workshops &#8211; one on how tech and AI can be used to promote International Mindedness, and other about AI and Creativity. I was expertly supported by Farah and her amazing facilitation skills.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The first workshop on International Mindedness explored the ways that technology is opening up opportunities to connect and collaborate on a global scale, but also recognising that many tools (especially those that use AI) will have bias, and that as educators we need the skills to recognise this. I shared some of the excellent work that my colleague Martyn Steiner has been doing using chatbots and other tools to promote International Mindedness and increase its visibility at Halcyon. We had some fascinating discussions and tested out various tools including virtual reality tours, ChatGPT for creative writing and Metaverse experiences. We also looked at popular digital tools (including social media apps like TikTok and educational tools like Google Earth) and assessed whether we thought they were harmful or beneficial to young people’s understanding of the world. There was some interested debate about TikTok, which some argued opens up young people’s understanding of global events, but also contains a lot of dis/misinformation &#8211; another reason that critical thinking is so important in today’s world.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The second workshop (to 140 educators!) focused on the ways that AI can spark creativity in students and teachers, and highlighted examples from Halcyon such as AI mask design, fashion design, creative writing chatbots and AI video production. We explored ways that AI can act as a ‘creative coach’, helping to prompt creative thinking without giving students the answers or writing/creating things for them. An example of this might be using ChatGPT to help to start a piece of creative writing, as in the example below: </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="571" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-1-1024x571.png" alt="" class="wp-image-19303" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-1-1024x571.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-1-300x167.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-1-768x428.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-1-1536x856.png 1536w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-1.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="666" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-2-1024x666.png" alt="" class="wp-image-19304" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-2-1024x666.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-2-300x195.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-2-768x500.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-2-1536x999.png 1536w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Faye-Blog-2.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Here, the AI acts as an encouraging coach, helping to break down a task that might seem overwhelming into steps and ask questions to prompt students to use their own creativity and grow their creative confidence.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>As well as leading and attending workshops, we also got to see some inspiring keynotes, and all three were extremely thought-provoking. The first, from<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/elaine-kasket/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> Elaine Kasket</a>, explored the significant increase in digital surveillance of young people and the harm this can cause. From CCTV and biometrics in schools to tracking behaviour and sharing every mistake students make with their parents (as happens in some schools with behaviour tracking apps), Elaine argued that we&#8217;re teaching children we don&#8217;t trust them and that they&#8217;re somehow unsafe. Her criticism of behaviour tracking tools particularly chimed with me and reminded me of some of the work of<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/naomi-fisher-psychologist/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> Naomi Fisher</a>. If you ever had your name moved to the ‘red light’ or ‘thundercloud’ in class because you’d fidgeted or not raised your hand to answer a question, you might have experienced some of that sense of public shaming. It’s worrying to think about how children must feel when not only are they ‘shamed’ in front of their peers, but their parents are also getting notifications when they make mistakes. It made me feel very grateful for our wellbeing-focused, restorative approach at Halcyon. </p>



<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/charlesfadel/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Charles Fadel</a> talked about AI, what it&#8217;s capable of, what it&#8217;s not, and the impact it&#8217;s having on education, including the knowledge and skills students are likely to need going into a future where they&#8217;re co-creating and collaborating with AI. He shared some examples of units that he and colleagues have designed at the Centre For Curriculum Redesign, that incorporate project based learning and key skills to thrive in the future. </p>



<p>Kimberley Wilson closed the conference with a keynote about brain health and nutrition, with an important reminder to look after ourselves as educators as well as our students. I enjoyed seeing half the auditorium reach for their water bottles when she talked about the impact of dehydration! It was an important reminder of the power of what we eat and how active we are in terms of our brain health, and gave me plenty of things to think about.&nbsp;</p>



<p>One key takeaway from the conference was that as IB educators, we need to raise awareness of the environmental impact of AI, and we’ll be exploring this in more detail over the coming months. Overall, it was a fantastic opportunity to see what other IB schools are doing but also to share some of the wonderful work our teachers do here at Halcyon.&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>The Halcyon innovation team is composed of Martin Steiner, Dr. Saba Lodhi, Faye Ellis, and Farah Ahmed.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Blueprint for Offline Innovation</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/a-blueprint-for-offline-innovation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Halcyon London International School]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 09:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[International Baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innovation team]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=19196</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Theory of Knowledge teacher, Farah Ahmed, writes for The Halcyon Blog, outlining how innovation is not just about technology. At Halcyon we embrace technology to amplify and enhance humanity’s capabilities, rather than replace them. We employ a Digital Learning Coach &#8211; unique, we believe in the UK education system &#8211; to help students and staff [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1440" height="810" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Farah-Workshop-edited.png" alt="Innovation Team member, Farah Ahmed leads an offline innovation workshop" class="wp-image-19199" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Farah-Workshop-edited.png 1440w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Farah-Workshop-edited-300x169.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Farah-Workshop-edited-1024x576.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Farah-Workshop-edited-768x432.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1440px) 100vw, 1440px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Halcyon staff take part in an offline workshop, led by Innovation Team member, Farah Ahmed during our summer staff development days.</figcaption></figure>



<p class="has-medium-font-size"><em>Theory of Knowledge teacher, Farah Ahmed, writes for The Halcyon Blog, outlining how innovation is not just about technology.</em></p>



<p>At Halcyon we embrace technology to amplify and enhance humanity’s capabilities, rather than replace them. We employ a Digital Learning Coach &#8211; unique, we believe in the UK education system &#8211; to help students and staff embrace tech tools to reduce workloads and advance research; we converse about the many ethical storms surrounding AI from chat-gpt to deep-fake-technology, and we preach paperless classrooms.</p>



<p>Recently <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2023/01/chatgpt-ai-economy-automation-jobs/672767/?utm_content=edit-promo&amp;utm_term=2023-02-06T22%3A18%3A01&amp;utm_source=linkedin&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_campaign=the-atlantic" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Atlantic</a> published an article highlighting the destabilising effects of AI to white collar jobs, lamenting that AI “creates content out of what is already out there, with no authority, no understanding, no ability to correct itself, no way to identify genuinely new or interesting ideas”. It reminded me of the benefits of an innovation team at a tech-facing school like Halcyon, which tries to do the opposite; to teach tech-savvy students to grapple with challenges like climate change and inequality, to take action rooted in human empathy, and to use their resources to do something different.</p>



<p>Last week, the team, composed of Martyn Steiner, Dr Sabahat Lodhi, Faye Ellis and myself, delivered a two-day workshop on international mindedness and service.</p>



<p>The days included conceptual understandings of international mindedness and effective service; along with workshops leading on strategies to make this work in our classrooms. In response to Faye, who introduced a number of technological tools &#8211; such as building digital museums to explore students’ intercultural heritages, and using data to create support systems for vulnerable communities &#8211; I decided my workshop on inquiry learning would offer a complementary set of skills; ones that could be built tech-free.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">A Tech-Free Innovation Workshop</h2>



<p>The first section of my workshop had staff compete in gamified tasks in order to answer simple, ‘factual’ inquiry questions like “What are students’ interests right now?” and “What global issues does your subject tackle?”. There is an obvious benefit to gamifying in the classroom – as one staff member said “I was scared when you told me I’d have to think hard in this workshop, but it didn’t feel like I was working at all!”.</p>



<p>The games were conducted sitting around a table, but part of my task was to have staff use their bodies; to link their thinking with physical movement. I created a very simple set-up: two whiteboards on either end of the room, one with a list of things that were important to students, the other with global issues happening in the world (all of which had been sourced from the brainstorming staff had done previously). Their task was to create a physical web, using a roll of string and some tape, between student interests and the world – for example, students are interested in clothes, which links to the global issue of fast fashion. The increase in activity also linked to an increase in complexity &#8211; now staff weren’t just answering factual questions like “what’s going on in the world” but more conceptual questions like “how does what I teach connect to students in meaningful ways?”.</p>



<p>This activity would have been far more efficient if I’d used the many excellent tools for mind mapping that are available online. But the goal was not efficiency. In fact, one of the first things staff noticed when reflecting on the activity was the pace: it took time to explain the connection, unravel the string and tape it to the board. That time allowed for the building of ideas: “that makes me think of…!”, “we could also add to that…!”. Often, when I use mind mapping softwares in class, I have to make a set of rules: make three posts, sign your name, comment on each other’s posts and so on. But in creating something tangible together, there was less emphasis on ownership individually and more on what the group was creating.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Collaborating Offline</h2>



<p>Moving offline made it easier to emphasise ATL (attention to learning) skills which are the backbone of an IB Education. When I began the making of our ‘web’, I did not give many instructions. I pointed to the boards, I held out the string and tape in my hands, and I allowed the group to organise themselves. I made sure to point out the ways staff worked in ways that felt service-oriented, like when a colleague was struggling to unravel the string fast enough, and another jumped up to help them. The point of the overall training was to encourage staff to deepen their understanding of the world and take action. In this workshop, I hoped to model the way that we must actively teach the skills students will need to make this a reality.</p>



<p>As Dr Lodhi noticed in her presentation on service, we need to tackle students’ helplessness about issues that seem out of their control, like climate change. We need to give them hope. When the web was finally created, it was impressive; “it’s like a work of art!” one colleague noticed. I made sure we took time to marvel at this big, physical representation of our group work. It was incontrovertible evidence of our collective power.</p>



<p>As the Atlantic notes: “AI can’t interview AI and labour experts, nor can it find historical documents, nor can it assess the quality of studies of technological change and employment”. All of these skills require understanding, human connection, imagination and critical thinking. Halcyon is a tech-facing school, but in ensuring that our workshop prioritised technological and non-technological, physical, face-to-face pedagogy, we were ensuring that students develop the wide range of skills needed for this new world order.</p>



<p>And, after all, being in a room together is still the primary benefit of a school, as opposed to the digital classrooms that dominated the pandemic.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Online and Offline Approaches Complement Each Other</h2>



<p>New technologies like AI and social media need to transform our teaching, as did the internet, photocopiers and other technologies of the past. I&#8217;ve learned a lot from my students’ interactions with technology, using games to create intrigue and friendly competition in my classroom. But I also feel a responsibility to remind students, and myself, that there are alternatives as well. That we can give up the lure of efficiency and endless information for the benefits of slowing down and learning from our community.</p>



<p><em>The Halcyon innovation team is composed of Martin Steiner, Dr. Saba Lodhi, Faye Ellis, and Farah Ahmed.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Empowering Students: 3 Ways To Develop Student Agency</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/empowering-students-student-agency/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Halcyon London International School]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 10:06:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[International Baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Wellbeing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cognitive coaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[restorative practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ib curriculum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IB]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=18958</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Every school is interested in academic outcomes, but few are willing to equip students with a genuine sense of student agency along the way.&#160; Our delivery of the IB is grounded in student agency. Students&#8217; contributions frame how we construct our curriculum. This includes the formation of their own clubs and explorations, venturing outside of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="229" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Blog-Web-Banner_Empowering-Students_Nito-Harvey_June-24-1024x229.png" alt="" class="wp-image-18960" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Blog-Web-Banner_Empowering-Students_Nito-Harvey_June-24-1024x229.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Blog-Web-Banner_Empowering-Students_Nito-Harvey_June-24-300x67.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Blog-Web-Banner_Empowering-Students_Nito-Harvey_June-24-768x172.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Blog-Web-Banner_Empowering-Students_Nito-Harvey_June-24.png 1146w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Every school is interested in academic outcomes, but few are willing to equip students with a genuine sense of student agency along the way.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Our delivery of the IB is grounded in student agency. Students&#8217; contributions frame how we construct our curriculum. This includes the formation of their own clubs and explorations, venturing outside of the classroom to fulfil their passions in the community, and informing recruitment. Student voice is built into the design of our school, capping the number of our classrooms to sixteen students which allows for stronger connection between staff and students, as well as offering shared, adaptable spaces, which encourages creativity, inspiration, and connection with staff.&nbsp;</p>



<p>However, fostering student agency is also about supporting students to help overcome social and emotional challenges. To help define this, we asked our wellbeing lead, Nito Harvey, to share three fundamental parts of our programme at Halcyon.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Cognitive Coaching</h2>



<p>Students engage in personalised one-on-one cognitive coaching sessions with their mentors, designed to empower them with the skills necessary for the development of their cognitive abilities. These sessions specifically target the enhancement of cognitive processes, including critical thinking, problem-solving, decision-making, and learning. This tailored approach seamlessly aligns with the principles of Social-Emotional Learning (SEL). Each week, students will have the opportunity to have a 15-20 mins&nbsp; coaching conversation with their mentors. Outside of these designated hours, students have access to their mentors at any given time and can request a coaching conversation.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Restorative Practices</strong></h3>



<p>Our comprehensive school-wide restorative approach has become ingrained in the fabric of our community, embodying a way of life for all. We cultivate a secure environment that fosters conversations aimed at fostering reconciliation, accountability, and reflection. This commitment is upheld through the thorough training of every staff member in restorative practices, ensuring that all students are well-acquainted with the process. As a result, students actively seek restorative conversations as a means to address and resolve conflicts. It is imperative that we have the support of our parents, they too have been exposed to the restorative process and have been encouraged to practice this at home.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Service in our community</h4>



<p>At Halcyon, we firmly believe in the inherent value each student brings to our community. Recognising their potential contributions, we provide diverse opportunities for students to actively engage in community service. At the core of student representation is our dynamic student council, which plays a pivotal role in orchestrating assemblies, staff development workshops, whole-school mentoring activities, and special events like International Night.</p>



<p>Moreover, students actively participate in key decision-making processes, meeting with the Senior leadership team on a regular basis and leading staff curriculum workshops. We aspire to empower students to wield their voices responsibly, fostering the skills to advocate not only for themselves but also for their peers. Through these initiatives, we cultivate a community where every student&#8217;s voice is not only heard but also respected and appreciated.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>IB Diploma Programme: How Halcyon Prepares Students For Successful Futures</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/ib-diploma-programme-successful-future/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Will McAdam]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 16:24:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[International Baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IB Diploma Programme]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alumni]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student agency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ib curriculum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Universities]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=18618</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As Grade 9 -10 Careers Day approaches, our recent Community Spotlight stars and startup founders, Thomas Beaudet and Cosmo Vollauschek (Class of 2022), reflect on how Halcyon&#8217;s IB Diploma Programme prepared them for prestigious degrees and developed the resilience required to found a startup. How Our IB Diploma Programme Opened A World Of Opportunity Thomas [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="341" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Community-Insight_Careers-Day_Cosmo-and-Thomas_Class-of-2022-1024x341.png" alt="IB Diploma Programme Graduates Cosmo and Thomas" class="wp-image-18619" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Community-Insight_Careers-Day_Cosmo-and-Thomas_Class-of-2022-1024x341.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Community-Insight_Careers-Day_Cosmo-and-Thomas_Class-of-2022-300x100.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Community-Insight_Careers-Day_Cosmo-and-Thomas_Class-of-2022-768x256.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Community-Insight_Careers-Day_Cosmo-and-Thomas_Class-of-2022-600x200.png 600w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Community-Insight_Careers-Day_Cosmo-and-Thomas_Class-of-2022.png 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>As Grade 9 -10 Careers Day approaches, our recent Community Spotlight stars and startup founders, Thomas Beaudet and Cosmo Vollauschek (Class of 2022), reflect on how Halcyon&#8217;s <a href="https://halcyonschool.com/academics/curriculum/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IB Diploma Programme</a> prepared them for prestigious degrees and developed the resilience required to found a startup.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How Our IB Diploma Programme Opened A World Of Opportunity</h2>



<p>Thomas and Cosmo are currently at university and they have embraced the international ethos Halcyon and the IB Diploma Programme promote. Both alumni secured places on prestigious degree programmes for which international travel is a core component &#8211; specifically to study in a variety of locations.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Thomas’s World Bachelor in Business, delivered by the <a href="https://hkust.edu.hk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST)</a>, has taken him to Los Angeles and next year will see him at <a href="https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/bocconi/sitopubblico_en/navigation+tree/home" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bocconi University</a>, Milan. The opportunity doesn’t end there, Tom notes. “In the fourth and final year, I will return to one of these institutions” where he will have “the opportunity to specialise”.</p>



<p><br>Similarly, Cosmo’s place at the renowned <a href="https://escp.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ESCP Business School</a> allowed him to “pursue this dream of travelling and immersing myself in different cultures”. His Bachelor of Science in Management has taken him to Turin, via London, before returning to Paris next year, which has allowed him “to pursue a high-quality degree while opening a world of professional opportunities internationally”.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Smoothing The Transition To University And Beyond</h2>



<p>Thomas highlighted that his time at Halcyon meant he could transition to university smoothly. “Halcyon gave us such freedom,” comments Cosmo, “such a landscape of topics to discover and a variety of people to meet, that at University, I felt as if I was entering a very similar environment, simply at scale, such that I felt completely ready to thrive.”</p>



<p>Cosmo seconded this. The transition “was smooth precisely because Halcyon and the IB Diploma Programme prepared us well for this unfamiliar learning environment.” But it is not just university for which Halcyon prepared them effectively, highlights Cosmo: “When I look at what I focus on professionally today, I actually find it quite easy to trace back to the courses I took at Halcyon”.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Developing Students Who Can Lead</h2>



<p>Thomas specifically highlights his “incredible DP Maths class” and how he will continue to use his passion for Maths when he graduates from HKUST and “enters the world of financial markets”. He credits the IB as a whole, and his English class in particular, for teaching him “to communicate through writing” &#8211; and as someone who co-leads a startup, he believes the ability to “communicate cogently” is a quality of a “good leader”.</p>



<p>Leadership “is something that’s embodied in more or less everything a Halcyon student is brought to do,” adds Cosmo, who also credits his English class and “so much of the critical thinking” for developing his leadership qualities. Building on this, he reiterates the importance of student autonomy, which is central to Halcyon’s approach to the IB and Wellbeing. “The autonomy Halcyon gave us forced us to experiment and try unfamiliar things. Ultimately, those are the moments where you learn the most”.</p>



<p>Halcyon’s delivery of the <a href="https://www.ibo.org/programmes/diploma-programme/curriculum/dp-core/creativity-activity-and-service/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IB Diploma Programme’s Creativity, Action and Service (CAS)</a> component is an example of the power this autonomy can have. Thomas and Cosmo’s start up, Equity &#8211; an educational board game that makes finance more fun and inclusive  “was, in many ways, conceived within Halcyon’s walls, most notably during our CAS project of delivering our Personal Finance and Stock Market course”.</p>



<p>With Grade 9-11 Careers Day approaching, current students have an opportunity to hear from inspiring speakers and consider, in earnest, how they might begin to shape their future. Thomas and Cosmo’s experience demonstrates the importance of embracing the opportunities offered by the International Baccalaureate and the opportunities to build autonomy, which are a hallmark of Halcyon’s holistic approach to education.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>Read Thomas and Cosmo&#8217;s Community Spotlight Blog</p>



<p>Visit Halcyon</p>



<p class="has-small-font-size"></p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Language Acquisition Trip: Embracing The World As Our Classroom</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/language-acquisition-trip/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Halcyon London International School]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 08:23:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[International Baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[language learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[school trip]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international baccalaureate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=18851</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article was originally published in Absolutely Magazine (April 2024). If you would like to know why Halcyon London International School offers an immersive Spanish language Acquisition trip to Cuenca, the answer is simple. It is the most enriching and comprehensive experience that we can present to our students to learn about global engagement, intercultural [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="229" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1146-x-256-px-1024x229.png" alt="" class="wp-image-18859" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1146-x-256-px-1024x229.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1146-x-256-px-300x67.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1146-x-256-px-768x172.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1146-x-256-px.png 1146w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>This article was originally published in <a href="https://issuu.com/zestmedialondon/docs/abs_apr2024_digital_upload_pcl" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Absolutely Magazine</a> (April 2024)</em>.</p>



<p>If you would like to know why Halcyon London International School offers an immersive Spanish language Acquisition trip to Cuenca, the answer is simple. It is the most enriching and comprehensive experience that we can present to our students to learn about global engagement, intercultural understanding, and multilingualism.</p>



<p>The International Baccalaureate (IB), taught at Halcyon,&nbsp; provides a platform for international trips, offering a window into the features, processes and craft of language, and the concept of culture, strengthening our understanding of the diverse ways of interpreting the world.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The peaceful, welcoming and quaint city of Cuenca is the perfect setting for our students to develop IB learner attributes that some of them did not know they already possess&nbsp; &#8211; starting with being open-minded: they&nbsp; stay with host families,embracing this new “lifestyle” with curiosity and respect.&nbsp;</p>



<p>During the immersive trip, they appreciate and fully enjoy experiences such as churros for breakfast, discovering and using idioms with locals and having tapas at midday.</p>



<p>They also participated in a wide range of workshops: flamenco, traditional folklore music, art and cooking &#8211; drawing out their creativity through authentic cultural encounters.</p>



<p>Students expanded their knowledge of art,&nbsp; natural history and the environment when visiting the Museo Abstract and the Paleontological&nbsp; Museum.&nbsp; Without great enthusiasm, they connected with nature while canoeing in the river Jucar and glimpsing bears in the natural park and Biosphere Reserve,<a href="https://www.parqueelhosquillo.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> El Hosquillo</a>.</p>



<p>As the days passed by, through their cultural interactions, our students increasingly felt the beating heart of the city as their own. They became more aware of new perspectives, the importance of communication and how openness to collaboration leads to more profound cultural experiences.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Having gained so much from Cuenca, students were keen to give back, addressing the core IB notion of Service Action. They visited&nbsp; ASPADEC, an organisation that successfully promotes the inclusion and professional development of the neurodiverse population in Cuenca. Our students showed their caring nature through gardening activities with the people that benefit from this organisation.</p>



<p>At Halcyon, our commitment to language learning goes beyond the school building and into the classroom of the world. We hope that our students will always treasure their time “living” in Cuenca as, of course, international trips run deeper than feasting on delicious street food.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Language acquisition offers many lifelong benefits. An increasing list of studies have noted that <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6168212/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">healthy people who are bilingual have slower rates of mental decline in old age</a>, they are less easily distracted, and they tend to have a better understanding of people generally, not just via the language they speak.  </p>



<p>Moreover, as noted by the International Baccalaureate Organisation, these trips enable students to communicate in a variety of modes, providing a linguistic and academic challenge for students in order to facilitate the best possible educational experience.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Travel allows us all to see the world as it is: a beautiful array of cultures and customs. Whether traveling as a student, with work, or simply to unwind, there is always something to be gained by opening our hearts and minds to the places in which we are lucky to find ourselves.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Halcyon Students Visit China</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/halcyon-students-visit-china/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Halcyon London International School]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 15:19:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[International Baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[school trip]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international baccalaureate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=18800</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Written by Tewolde Hagos. We embarked on a thrilling journey from our cosmopolitan London to the distant lands of modern and ancient China, immersing ourselves in its vibrant local culture.  This learning adventure was about more than just gaining knowledge about China; it was a journey of harnessing and honing outdoor skills, trading and exploring [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="341" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1-1024x341.png" alt="" class="wp-image-18825" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1-1024x341.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1-300x100.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1-768x256.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Copy-of-Copy-of-Halcyon-Customise-Headers-1.png 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Written by Tewolde Hagos.</p>



<p>We embarked on a thrilling journey from our cosmopolitan London to the distant lands of modern and ancient China, immersing ourselves in its vibrant local culture. </p>



<p>This learning adventure was about more than just gaining knowledge about China; it was a journey of harnessing and honing outdoor skills, trading and exploring local markets, conquering physical challenges, fostering team-building, mastering culinary skills with nuanced local chefs, and refining language, performance, and presentation skills. So, get ready and prepare a cuppa to read about the unique and unforgettable experiences we had during our stay in China and the places we visited with joy, excitement, curiosity, and inquiry, fostering and acknowledging cultural differences while delving into the Theory of Knowledge: How culture influences knowledge production and communication. We started our journey in Beijing and then explored Chengdu, Xi&#8217;an, and their surrounding cities before concluding our learning expedition back in Beijing.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Beijing</h2>



<p>The Great Wall, The Forbidden City, Summer Palace, Tiananmen Square</p>



<p>We started our learning adventure in Beijing and visited Tiananmen Square, The Forbidden City, The Great Wall, and the Summer Palace—all iconic landmarks in Beijing, China.</p>



<p>Tiananmen Square, a large city square in the centre of Beijing, is also known for its historical and cultural significance. It includes the Tiananmen Tower, the Monument to the People&#8217;s Heroes, the Great Hall of the People, and the Mao Zedong Memorial Hall.<br></p>



<p>The Forbidden City, with its intricate architecture and rich history, was the Chinese imperial palace from the Ming dynasty to the end of the Qing dynasty. Just north of the Forbidden City, we continued our walk on Jingshan Park, a park known for its artificial hill, Jingshan Hill (also known as Coal Hill), which offers panoramic views of the Forbidden City and the surrounding cityscape. Jingshan Park is a popular destination for locals and tourists, offering a serene escape from the bustling city below and stunning views of Beijing&#8217;s historic landmarks. Hence, our visit was greeted with a long queue of tourists and checkpoints.</p>



<p>The Great Wall, a marvel of ancient engineering, stretches thousands of miles across northern China, leaving us all amused by its engineering and significance in old China. It was a great experience to explore what is known and a piece of common knowledge to some of us. However, being there physically and learning more from our education tourist guide about its purpose of building with historical events was sensationally insightful to all of us visiting.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Before visiting the Great Wall of China, our students visited a local market, which allowed our Mandarin students to explore their Chinese language and communicate with the locals while trading. It was a fun, unforgettable, happy experience that kept us laughing while we discussed our local market bargaining experience throughout the trip. We all had one thing in common: we kept looking for local souvenir purchases for our families, loved ones, colleagues, and friends back in London.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In Beijing&#8217;s densely populated area, we had a culinary session at Beijinger&#8217;s kitchen cooking class, which is a walking distance from the famous Confucius temple. We made our own local dumplings, guided and supervised by local chiefs, and fed on what we had created, which was so much fun. Then, to feed our souls with knowledge and find an answer to our curiosity of being IB learners interested in Chinese philosophy, history, and culture, we spent an afternoon visiting The Beijing Temple of Confucius, which is one of the most prominent Confucian temples in China and serves as a place of worship and education dedicated to the memory of the great Chinese philosopher and educator. The temple complex includes halls, pavilions, courtyards, housing statues, large stone tablets(commemorating Confucius&#8217;s teachings and contributions to Chinese philosophy and culture), and other cultural relics related to Confucianism. As our students continued to admire and explore their own philosophies of life, we were immersed in appreciating and learning all about Confucius from our local and best education tourist guides. It was a great feeling to realise that we were standing in pride and with our own life philosophy at a place where the great philosopher stood and taught his philosophy to his disciples and students 2500 years ago.Â&nbsp;</p>



<p>Indeed, whether it is us on this China trip or you, the reader of this blog ( you are awesome for reading this far), would agree with one of the vital central virtues in Confucian ethics philosophy concept:&#8221; Ren&#8221;, often translated as &#8220;benevolence,&#8221; &#8220;humaneness,&#8221; or &#8220;goodness,&#8221;. It emphasises the importance of cultivating virtuous relationships with others and treating them with empathy, kindness, and compassion.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Chengdu</strong></h3>



<p>Grand Budha, Chengdu Panda Breeding Research Center, Traditional Chinese tea house performance.</p>



<p>&nbsp;We are in the coach heading to Leshan, the world&#8217;s largest Buddha. This impressive statue is the largest stone Buddha statue in the world and is renowned for its sheer size and architectural grandeur, which took 90 years to finish during the Tang Dynasty. The statue stands at a towering height of about 71 meters (233 feet) and is carved into the cliffside, facing Mount Emei in Leshan. The Leshan Giant Buddha is an impressive feat of ancient engineering and craftsmanship and holds cultural and religious significance as a symbol of Buddhist faith and teachings. The surroundings are full of Buddhist philosophy and way of life, quoting one,&#8217; &#8220;There is no road to happiness, happiness itself is the road&#8221;.</p>



<p>Before visiting Leashan&#8217;s grand Budha statue, yesterday was an exhilarating volunteering work experience for our students and us travelling staff at the Chengdu Panda Breeding Research Center. The work involved caring for pandas, from preparing their food, panda cake (from bamboo), as you might know, students are engaged in SA (service as action) and CAS (creative activity service) as part of the IB curriculum requirements.</p>



<p>In the former project, students in the MYP are engaged in services that positively impact communities and the environment.</p>



<p>In the latter IBDP, students are more inclined to participate in activities demonstrating perseverance and initiative to develop collaboration, problem-solving, and decision-making skills. These enable students to enhance their personal and interpersonal development by learning through experience, and our students are courageous and resiliently engaged in voluntary work at the Panda Centre. This is designed to allow students to self-determination and collaborate with others, fostering a sense of accomplishment and enjoyment for their work.</p>



<p>To echo what the person who has led our activity at the Chengdu Dujiangyan Panda Center said, “The students completed the service faster than the time allocated and were very efficient in doing the work given to them.! And our students now have a certificate issued for their accomplishments.”</p>



<p>Furthermore, to add to what Ella (one of our students on this tour) said about the activity in the panda breeding research centre, &#8220;this is good for my CV&#8221;. Yes, this could be part of the puzzle for students&#8217; future careers, especially as some of them are not far from stepping into studying at university for their career aspirations, this experience could be incorporated into their university applications, and this could give them the edge in the selection.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Finally, students will record their experiences and reflections on ManageBac. Upon completion, the reflection will be approved and commented on by their supervisors at school.</p>



<p>Indeed, personally, the experience contributed to the panda population flourishing and surviving extinction, and I felt satisfied with a sense of accomplishment and pride in contributing to a sustainable earth.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Our late afternoons were full of activities that prolonged to an early evening, whether it was watching the world-renowned face-changing act or a captivating performance that is part of the Sichuan Opera, a traditional form of Chinese opera that originated in Sichuan Province, China. One of the most famous elements of Sichuan Opera is the art of face-changing (from a paper mask without the audience releasing how it&#8217;s done). We enjoyed this unique form of entertainment while sipping on tea in a traditional tea house, immersing ourselves in the rich cultural heritage of Sichuan Province. Or a mesmerising and jaw-dropping acrobatic show at the Beijing Opera House on our second day of arrival in China.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Xian</h4>



<p>Terracotta Warriors, Muslim Quarter and a bike ride.</p>



<p>Terracotta Warriors: Located near Xi&#8217;an city, the Terracotta Army is one of the most significant archaeological discoveries in the world. It consists of thousands of life-sized terracotta sculptures depicting the armies of Qin Shi Huang, the first Emperor of China. Each warrior has unique features and details, representing the military might of the Qin Dynasty. Visiting the Terracotta Warriors offered our students another fascinating glimpse into ancient Chinese history and craftsmanship. Later in the afternoon, our students visited a local Terracotta Warriors factory and had the chance to make their own Terracotta warrior, which was another fun activity we did.</p>



<p>We visited the Muslim Quarter in Xi&#8217;an City, featuring narrow alleys lined with traditional shops and stalls. Students were able to explore a variety of authentic Chinese-Muslim settings, browse unique souvenirs, and immerse themselves in the vibrant atmosphere of this cultural place. The next day, we all enjoyed riding a bike on top of the Xi&#8217;an City Wall, one of China&#8217;s oldest and best-preserved city walls.</p>



<p>As our learning adventure continued, we visited a local school. This was a great social experience for our students, and we were all humbled by the musical reception of the school band. After working together as a team visiting the school&#8217;s classroom, involving calligraphy sessions and assembling technology products such as compass, musical instruments, and papercraft artwork, we then had a football match, which was concluded with the only score scored by Halcyon.</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading">The Return Home</h5>



<p>On our last day in Beijing, before returning to our palaces and dearly missed families in London, we visited the Summer Palace, a vast ensemble of lakes, gardens, and palaces that served as a retreat for emperors during the Qing dynasty. These landmarks represent centuries of Chinese history and culture, enriching our learning outcomes for the trip.</p>



<p>Throughout our journey, amidst savouring the delicious array of Chinese cuisine, each dish a delightful reflection of the unique flavours of every province we traversed, we found ourselves nourishing not only our bodies but also our minds and spirits with the rich tapestry of China&#8217;s ancient and modern history and culture. This immersive experience has served as a profound catalyst, inspiring us to seek avenues for personal growth, resilience, and unity, drawing strength from the lessons of the past to forge a brighter, more tolerant, and peaceful future.</p>



<p>Thank you to Ms Lin for orchestrating what can only be described as a once-in-a-lifetime odyssey—a journey that will forever remain etched in our memories. And to Halcyon, we express our deepest gratitude for allowing us to transcend classroom walls and immerse ourselves in the living classroom of China.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Every moment was a lesson in self-discovery and cultural understanding, as each travelling student discovered part of the puzzle to fulfil their unique potential.</p>



<p>To our remarkable students, the true stars of our expedition, I offer my utmost admiration and appreciation. Your compassion, kindness, and respect for one another and our host country&#8217;s customs exemplify the finest virtues of global citizens. Your grace, creativity, generosity, boundless curiosity, intellect, and resilience shone brightly throughout our travels, illuminating our path. Well done to each and every one of you—you have truly made this journey an extraordinary success.</p>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-4">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow" style="flex-basis:100%">
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="724" height="1024" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-1-724x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-18814" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-1-724x1024.jpeg 724w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-1-212x300.jpeg 212w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-1-768x1086.jpeg 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-1-1086x1536.jpeg 1086w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-1.jpeg 1131w" sizes="(max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="724" height="1024" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-2-724x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-18813" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-2-724x1024.jpeg 724w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-2-212x300.jpeg 212w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-2-768x1086.jpeg 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-2-1086x1536.jpeg 1086w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-2.jpeg 1131w" sizes="(max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="724" height="1024" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-3-724x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-18816" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-3-724x1024.jpeg 724w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-3-212x300.jpeg 212w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-3-768x1086.jpeg 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-3-1086x1536.jpeg 1086w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-3.jpeg 1131w" sizes="(max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="724" height="1024" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-4-724x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-18815" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-4-724x1024.jpeg 724w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-4-212x300.jpeg 212w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-4-768x1086.jpeg 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-4-1086x1536.jpeg 1086w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-4.jpeg 1131w" sizes="(max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="576" height="1024" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-5-576x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-18811" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-5-576x1024.jpeg 576w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-5-169x300.jpeg 169w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-5-768x1365.jpeg 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-5-864x1536.jpeg 864w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-5.jpeg 900w" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="576" height="1024" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-6-576x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-18812" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-6-576x1024.jpeg 576w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-6-169x300.jpeg 169w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-6-768x1365.jpeg 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-6-864x1536.jpeg 864w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-6.jpeg 900w" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="576" height="1024" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-Trip-1-576x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-18821" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-Trip-1-576x1024.png 576w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-Trip-1-169x300.png 169w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-Trip-1-768x1365.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-Trip-1-864x1536.png 864w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-Trip-1.png 900w" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="682" height="1024" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-8-682x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-18817" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-8-682x1024.jpeg 682w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-8-200x300.jpeg 200w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-8-768x1153.jpeg 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-8-1023x1536.jpeg 1023w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-8.jpeg 1066w" sizes="(max-width: 682px) 100vw, 682px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="576" height="1024" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-9-576x1024.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-18818" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-9-576x1024.jpeg 576w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-9-169x300.jpeg 169w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-9-768x1365.jpeg 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-9-864x1536.jpeg 864w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/China-9.jpeg 900w" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px" /></figure>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Encouraging A Desire To Learn Is The Key To Academic Success</title>
		<link>https://halcyonschool.com/blog/desire-to-learn-academic-success/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Halcyon London International School]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 13:35:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[International Baccalaureate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Wellbeing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Agency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[university destinations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[academic excellence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international baccalaureate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://halcyonschool.com/?p=18891</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It’s no secret that nurturing wellbeing is a key driver for academic success. As our director, Barry Mansfield, carefully articulated in this article for Independent Schools Magazine, wellbeing is a term that needs to be grounded in practicality. For Halcyon, we deliver this with coaching, wellbeing initiatives, community engagement, and guiding principles.&#160; These wellbeing initiatives [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="229" src="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Blog-Web-Banner_Wellbeing-and-Uni-Destinations_Asil-Al-Shammari-1024x229.png" alt="" class="wp-image-18890" srcset="https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Blog-Web-Banner_Wellbeing-and-Uni-Destinations_Asil-Al-Shammari-1024x229.png 1024w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Blog-Web-Banner_Wellbeing-and-Uni-Destinations_Asil-Al-Shammari-300x67.png 300w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Blog-Web-Banner_Wellbeing-and-Uni-Destinations_Asil-Al-Shammari-768x172.png 768w, https://halcyonschool.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Blog-Web-Banner_Wellbeing-and-Uni-Destinations_Asil-Al-Shammari.png 1146w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>It’s no secret that nurturing wellbeing is a key driver for academic success. As our director, Barry Mansfield, carefully articulated in this article for <a href="https://www.independentschoolsmagazine.co.uk/issues/2024-february/index.html#p=12" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Independent</a><a href="https://www.independentschoolsmagazine.co.uk/issues/2024-february/index.html#p=12" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> Schools Magazine</a>, wellbeing is a term that needs to be grounded in practicality. For Halcyon, we deliver this with coaching, wellbeing initiatives, community engagement, and guiding principles.&nbsp;</p>



<p>These wellbeing initiatives aren’t an aside &#8211; they are penned into our delivery of the IB.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Wellbeing is a core determinant to university success</h3>



<p>Students are equipped with essential emotional tools to understand themselves, express their thoughts and emotions, and overcome challenges with resilience. Our wellbeing programmes function as core determinants to university success and life beyond school.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Although many IB schools provide basic mentorship programmes, our blend of restorative practices and one-to-one cognitive coaching sessions ensures we gain a full picture of our students based on qualitative evidence.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">PSHE, emotional intelligence and real-world applications</h4>



<p>This information is gathered through our robust PSHE curriculum where all students study a unit on health and wellbeing for a semester. In this unit, they explore different topics related to physical, mental and emotional wellbeing, which further embed SEL skills like self-and-social awareness.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As an example, students learn emotional intelligence, by recognising how emotions like ‘awe’ affect the physiology and psychology of the human body and mind. They learn about self-awareness and how to develop it, and study different mental health disorders, which broadens their emotional vocabulary and awareness.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>This pragmatism fuels a <em>desire to learn</em>. It empowers students to advocate for themselves and find their voice within our community. An example is our recent Interdisciplinary Unit (IDU) days, whereby students weave together subjects – such as maths and science – to unpack real world issues.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For example, G6 students (11-12 years) studied zoo habitat design at London Zoo. They compiled data about animal behaviour –&nbsp;such as how much time they spend eating, walking, drinking or swimming in the wild –&nbsp;before suggesting improvements the zoo could make about the enclosures.<br><br>As a result, students were empowered to seek out relevant real-world learning opportunities that resonate with their interests, passions, and values, whether in higher education or future careers.</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading">Experiential Learning Opportunities</h5>



<p>Furthermore, our school community offers rich experiential learning opportunities, where students can develop interpersonal skills and uncover latent talents. Encouraging autonomy, curiosity and advocacy, we inspire students to explore new avenues for themselves and their peers, driving exploration and broadening potential career paths.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Students are able to engage in a variety of clubs through the Extra-Curricular Activity (ECA) program and create their own club to develop and share their interests.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The student-led Debate Club, for example, is a locus of heated political discussion.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Students from Grade 6-11 (11-17 years) become activists in their own right, researching and speaking on a variety of topical issues – such as artificial intelligence, immigration, sex-ed, or climate change –&nbsp; before putting their arguments to the test against teachers.</p>



<p>By encouraging whole-class discussion surrounding political or school reform, classrooms become a battlefield of high-engagement and learning.</p>



<h6 class="wp-block-heading">Our Careers Programme</h6>



<p>Another chapter is our careers programme. This spans from the Middle Years Programme (MYP, 11-16 years) through to the Diploma Programme (DP, 16-18 years), placing a strong emphasis on career exploration and preparedness. It begins in G9 (14-15 years), where students embark on a path of self-discovery through a careers interest assessment. This initial step sparks conversations about potential career avenues that align with their interests, as well as how students are engaging in these interests through their ECAs.</p>



<p>Building upon this foundation, G10 students (15-16 years) engage in psychometric tests designed to evaluate their aptitude across various areas, such as abstract thinking, mechanical, spatial, numerical, and verbal skills. The insights gained from these assessments help students identify career fields and degree pathways that best match their unique skill set and learning style.</p>



<p>The results obtained in G9 and G10 serve as catalysts for meaningful discussions around DP subject selections, extracurricular pursuits, and opportunities for super curricular engagement. By aligning their academic pursuits with their newfound interests and strengths, students are empowered to shape their school profile in a way that resonates with their future aspirations.</p>



<p>Our work experience programme and annual careers day further enrich this journey, providing students with firsthand exposure to diverse career options and pathways. As they progress into the DP, students are equipped with the confidence and clarity needed to make informed decisions regarding their higher education and career choices.</p>



<p>At every stage of their academic journey, our goal is to inspire and empower students to explore, discover, and pursue fulfilling career paths that resonate with their passions and potential. Although young, we have succeeded in connecting students with their passions, noted by our close, sustained relationship with alumni, and the <a href="https://halcyonschool.com/graduate-destinations/">breadth of </a><a href="https://halcyonschool.com/graduate-destinations/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">universities</a><a href="https://halcyonschool.com/graduate-destinations/"> and subjects our students have successfully fulfilled</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Read more about our <a href="https://halcyonschool.com/graduate-destinations/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">leavers&#8217; destinations</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>

<!--
Performance optimized by W3 Total Cache. Learn more: https://www.boldgrid.com/w3-total-cache/

Page Caching using Disk: Enhanced (Page is feed) 

Served from: halcyonschool.com @ 2024-11-20 14:25:26 by W3 Total Cache
-->